Ed Leffingwell Jack Smith Curatorial Files 1962-2010 (Bulk 1993-1998) MSS 380
Fales Library and Special Collections
Ed Leffingwell Jack Smith Curatorial Files
Bulk, 1993-1998
1962-2010 (Bulk 1993-1998)
MSS 380
Fales Library and Special Collections
5.0 linear feet (2 Record Cartons, 1 Media Box, Seven Oversize Folders)
The Edward Leffingwell Jack Smith Curatorial Files include correspondence, manuscripts, clippings and audio recordings associated with Leffingwell’s organization of the exhibition “Jack Smith: Flaming Creature” at P.S. 1 (New York) and associated printed matter, including material created by Jack Smith.
Scope and Content
The Edward Leffingwell Jack Smith Curatorial Files contain research material acquired by Edward Leffingwell as he organized the exhibition “Jack Smith: Flaming Creature” for New York’s P.S. 1 Museum and his own record of the exhibition’s development and execution. It includes correspondence, notebooks, printed material, newspaper clippings, audio recordings, posters, flyers and other ephemera. The bulk of collection was created or assembled while Leffingwell was actively planning the exhibition (1993 to 1997), and most of the documents that were produced in the 1960s and 1970s exists here as photocopies – many of which feature Leffingwell’s annotations.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
Series I: Jack Smith Research
Series I contains correspondence between Jack Smith and his contemporaries as well as follow-up from Leffingwell, notebooks and scripts written by Smith, flyers and posters advertising Smith performances and screenings, interviews with Smith from periodicals or transcribed by Leffingwell, articles about Smith written by critics, journalists and fellow artists, and some contextual information, including Smith’s censorship and accusations of obscenity.
Series II: Leffingwell’s Correspondence and Writing
Series II contains material related to Leffingwell's organization of “Jack Smith: Flaming Creature,” including an annotated bibliography, a checklist of the archival material assembled for the exhibition, Leffingwell’s correspondence with other artists and critics, drafts of material Leffingwell wrote for the exhibition and its associated publications, and newspaper clippings of the show’s reviews, as well as some material relating to subsequent Smith exhibitions.
Series III: Audio
Series III contains audio material recorded onto cassette tapes, including archival material of Smith’s rehearsals, performances, and interviews as well as interviews conducted by Leffingwell. The third subseries contains a variety of material, including additional Smith recordings, stock audio and recordings of radio advertisements, albums of commercially distributed music, and a recording of a Jack Smith memorial.
Biographical Note
Edward Leffingwell (b. 1941) is an art critic and curator. He received his master’s degree in art history from the University of Cincinnati, with a focus on 19th-Century American portraiture, and then moved to Los Angeles, where he wrote for the Los Angeles Free Press and collaborated with the Abstract Expressionist sculptor John Chamberlain. In the 1980s he was the Director of Programming at New York’s Institute for Art and Urban Resources (now MoMA P.S. 1) and then the Director of Visual Art for the City of Los Angeles Cultural Affairs Department, before serving as Los Angeles’s corresponding editor for Art in America.
Shortly after leaving the Cultural Affairs Department, Leffingwell began research on the experimental filmmaker and performance artist Jack Smith (1931-1989), for what would eventually become Smith’s first career retrospective. “Jack Smith: Flaming Creature” opened at P.S. 1 in October 1997 and ran until March 1998, prompting a feature in Artforum and favorable mention elsewhere. Reviewing the exhibition for The New York Times, Holland Cotter wrote that it was “not only an exhaustive archival tour of Smith's career but also a model monographic approach to an artist much of whose primary work was in the ephemeral medium of performance.” In conjunction with the exhibition, Leffingwell oversaw an experimental biography that also served as an exhibition guide, Flaming Creature: Jack Smith, His Amazing Life and Times (from Serpent's Tail Books) and edited a collection of Smith’s writings, Wait for Me at the Bottom of the Pool, (from Serpent’s Tail's New York-based imprint, High Risk).
Following the Jack Smith exhibition, Leffingwell went to Sao Paolo to cover the emerging art scene for Art in America, and remained the magazine's corresponding editor from Brazil until 2012. Over the course of his career, Leffingwell wrote fourteen books and exhibition guides, as well as dozens of articles about 19th and 20th-Century art, with a strong focus on conceptual works.
Sources:
Venant, Elizabeth. “New Muni Director a Man With a Mission.” Los Angeles Times, December 8, 1988.
Muchnic, Suzanne. "Shake-Up at Municipal Art Gallery." Los Angeles Times, July 8, 1992.
Cotter, Holland. “P.S. 1 Review/Art; All Over the Lot (The Back Lot, Too).” The New York Times, October 31, 1997.
Flaming Creature: Jack Smith, His Amazing Life and Times. editor Edward Leffingwell. London: Serpent's Tail Books, 1997.
Smith, Jack. Wait for Me at the Bottom of the Pool. editor Edward Leffingwell. New York: High Risk, 1997.
Art in America (1995-2012)
Related Materials at Fales Library and Special Collections
(Edward Leffingwell & Jack Smith)
The Serpent's Tail/High Risk Archives
The Stefan Brecht Papers
(Edward Leffingwell)
The Exit Art Archive
(Jack Smith)
The Sylvère Lotringer Papers and Semiotext(e) Archive
The John Vaccaro and the Play-House of the Ridiculous Papers
The Ira Silverberg Papers
"Not Only This, But New Language Beckons Us" Exhibition Archive
Arrangement
The Edward Leffingwell Jack Smith Curatorial Files are arranged in Leffingwell’s original order, retaining his folder titles and series separations (though in some instances, additional information has been added parenthetically). The files are grouped into two series of manuscript material and a series of audio media that features subseries, as well as an oversize series with two subseries reflecting the original manuscript series separations. Due to the broad date ranges contained within each folder, the first two series have been organized alphabetically, whereas the audio recordings are organized chronologically (where possible).
Series I: Jack Smith Material
Series II: Leffingwell’s Writing and Correspondence
Series III: Audio
Subseries A: Jack Smith
Subseries B: Leffingwell Interviews
Subseries C: Miscellaneous
Oversize Series:
Series I: Jack Smith Material
Series II: Leffingwell’s Writing and Correspondence
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Provenance
The collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections by Ed Leffingwell in 2013, and transferred directly from Leffingwell's apartment to the Library.
Arcade, Penny; Bateman, Lisa; Hoberman, J.; Leffingwell, Ed; Markopoulos, Gregory; Mekas, Jonas; Moon, Michael; Rosenthal, Irving 1930-; Smith, Jack 1932-1989; Tartaglia, Jerry; Tavel, Ronald; Vaccaro, John; Wilson, Robert 1941-; Zazeela, Marian; Art criticism.; Art |x Censorship |z United States.; Art |x Exhibitions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Audiocassettes.; Experimental films.; Experimental theater.; Independent filmmakers |z United States.; Performance art.
- Series I: Jack Smith Research
  Scope and Content
  Series I contains correspondence between Jack Smith and his contemporaries as well as follow-up from Leffingwell, copies of notebooks and scripts written by Smith, flyers and posters advertising Smith performances and screenings, interviews with Smith from periodicals or transcribed by Leffingwell, articles about Smith written by critics, journalists and fellow artists, and some contextual information, including Smith’s censorship and accusations of obscenity.
  - Joan Adler, 1995-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kenneth Anger, 1964-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Penny Arcade, 1990-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lisa Bateman, 1993-1998; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - J. Hoberman, 1984-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gregory Markopoulos, 1964-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jonas Mekas (& Anthology Film Archive), 1965-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Irving Rosenthal, 1967-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jack Smith: Censorship [1 of 2], 1964-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jack Smith: Censorship [2 of 2], 1964-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jack Smith: Clash of the Brassiere Goddesses, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jack Smith: Correspondence, 1963-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jack Smith: Films (No President & Buzzards Over Baghdad), 1967-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jack Smith: in Brazil, 1967-1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jack Smith: in Italy, 1977-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jack Smith: Interviews [1 of 3], 1964-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Jack Smith: Interviews [2 of 3], 1964-1997, undated (Box 1, Box 17)
  - Jack Smith: Interviews [3 of 3], 1964-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Jack Smith: Notebook ("Brassieres For Men"), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jack Smith: Notebook ("Rip Torn Press Release"), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Jack Smith: Photocopies, 1965-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jack Smith: Poster Copies, 1963-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Jack Smith: The Secret of Rented Island, 1976-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jack Smith: Titles, scripts, etc., 1963-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jack Smith: Writings [1 of 5], 1964-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jack Smith: Writings [2 of 5], 1964-1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Jack Smith: Writings [3 of 5], 1965-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jack Smith: Writings [4 of 5], 1964-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jack Smith: Writings [5 of 5], 1981-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Susan Sontag (Michael Moon), 1964-1995 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jerry Tartaglia, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ronald Tavel [1 of 2], 1966-1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ronald Tavel [2 of 2], 1996-1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ron Vawter ("Roy Cohn/Jack Smith"), 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Andy Warhol, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Robert Wilson, 1965-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Marian Zazeela/LaMonte Young, 1962-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Series II: Leffingwell Correspondence & Writing
  Series II contains material related to Leffingwell's organization of “Jack Smith: Flaming Creature,” including an annotated bibliography, a checklist of the archival material assembled for the exhibition, Leffingwell’s correspondence with other artists and critics, drafts of material Leffingwell wrote for the exhibition and its associated publications, and newspaper clippings of the show’s reviews, as well as some material relating to subsequent Smith exhibitions.
  - Jack Smith Bibliography, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jack Smith Checklist/Archive, 1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Jack Smith Correspondence [1 of 6], 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jack Smith Correspondence [2 of 6], 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jack Smith Correspondence [3 of 6], 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jack Smith Correspondence [4 of 6], 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jack Smith Correspondence [5 of 6], 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jack Smith Correspondence [6 of 6], 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Essays (Research Material), 1963-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Introduction to Biography 'Jack Smith: Flaming Creature', 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Vampires, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Loose Materials [1 of 5] - Concise Chronology, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Loose Materials [2 of 5] - Jack Smith Working Chronology, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Loose Materials [3 of 5], 1992-2010 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Loose Materials [4 of 5] - Artforum vol. 36 no. 2 (October 1997) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Loose Materials [5 of 5] - Mousse no. 24 (Summer 2010) (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series III: Audio
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  Series III contains audio material recorded onto cassette tapes, including archival material of Smith’s rehearsals, performances, and interviews as well as interviews conducted by Leffingwell. The third subseries contains a variety of material, including additional Smith recordings, stock audio and recordings of radio advertisements, albums of commercially distributed music, and a recording of a Jack Smith memorial.
  - Subseries A: Jack Smith Performances & Interviews
    - Jack Smith: Les Evening Gown Damnées on Tony Conrad's Audio ArtKive 001, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0001)
      Access CD available.
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
      Original format: 1/4" audiocassette
      Duration: Unknown
    - Jack Smith: Les Evening Gown Damnées on Tony Conrad's Audio ArtKive 002, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0002)
    - Secret of Rented Island, 1977 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0003)
      Access CD available. Please request part one and part two.
    - Sylvère Lotringer Interview, 1978 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0004)
    - Jack Smith in Genoa (Il Gergo Inquieto), Feb. 1981 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0005)
    - Penguin Panic Boston, Sept. 1981 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0006)
    - Jack Smith: "What's Underground About Marshmallows?", Oct. 1981 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0007)
    - Jack Smith Compilation, 1981 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0008)
    - Jack Smith: Toronto Lecture, Art & Art History, 1984 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0009)
    - Performance & Music and Story of Sacrifice of Abraham, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0010)
    - RAIN - music and thunder, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0011)
    - Rehearsal (à la Chekhov), undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0012)
    - A: Repetitive Reheasal Jack Smith + Woman's Voice + Man's Voice as actors + directors B: Music, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0013)
  - Subseries B: Ed Leffingwell Interviews on Jack Smith
    - John Vaccaro/Gwen Thomas, Taylor Meade, September 29-30, 1993 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0014)
    - Stanton Kaye, August 29, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0015)
    - Jerry Tartaglia, September 20, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0016)
    - Gaby Rodgers, September 21, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0017)
    - Marian Zazeela/La Monte Young [1 of 2], September 23, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0018)
    - Marian Zazeela/La Monte Young [2 of 2], September 23, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0019)
    - McTighe, September 23, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0020)
    - Telephone Interview - Hans Breder (Iowa City), November 13, 1995 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0021)
    - Joan Jonas (A side only), February 5, 1996 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0022)
    - Louie Walden Interview, August 20, 1996 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0023)
    - Ronald Tavel [1 of 3], August 23, 1996 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0024)
    - Ronald Tavel [2 of 3], August 23, 1996 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0025)
    - Ronald Tavel [3 of 3], August 23, 1996 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0026)
    - Cobra Soundtrack plus Jack Smith on street, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0027)
    - Interview with John Vaccaro, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0028)
    - Jonas Mekas, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0029)
  - Subseries C: Miscellaneous Audio
    - Two Moods - G.S. Sachdev, 1979 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0030)
    - Rag Kambhoji - The Dagar Brothers, 1988 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0031)
    - Jack Smith feature on WFUV (Fordham), 1998 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0032)
    - KBZ200 "Live" in München, 1999 (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0033)
    - Brit. Interview + Sound FX, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0034)
    - Commercials on Radio, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0035)
    - damaged/blank 2, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0036)
    - Hawaiian Holiday - Kaino Koiotto's Hilo Hawaiians, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0037)
    - Jack Smith / Compilation - Astur Piarella, Revolution de Tango, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0038)
    - Jack Smith Demo Tape - Titled "La Bamba" (Mixed Commercials), undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0039)
    - Jack Smith Program Music, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0040)
    - Memorial Tape, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0041)
    - North African Music, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0042)
    - WBAI / Jamaican Politics Show + Music, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0043)
    - WBAI, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0044)
    - unlabelled, undated (Box 3, Media ID: 380.0045)
- Oversize Materials
  - Oversize Series I: Jack Smith Research
    - "Pack Rat of the Avant-Garde" by Amy Taubin (from Box 1 Folder 7, Jonas Mekas (& Anthology Film Archive)), 1987 (Map-case 1, Drawer F)
    - "New American Cinema: Five Years Later" (from Box 1 Folder 9, Jack Smith: Censorship [1 of 2]), 1965 (Map-case 1, Drawer F)
    - "Roy Cohn/Jack Smith" Program & "The Theatre of Jack Smith" (from Box 1 Folder 34, Ron Vawter), undated (Map-case 1, Drawer F)
    - At The Warhol: Museum Guide (from Box 1 Folder 21: Jack Smith Photocopies), 1998 (Map-case 1, Drawer F)
    - 05/06.95 - May/June at the Wexner Center for the Arts (from Box 1 Folder 34, Ron Vawter), 1995 (Map-case 1, Drawer F)
  - Oversize Series II: Leffingwell Correspondence
    - Photo Composite of Jack Smith, from Susanna Wilson (from Box 2 Folder 7, Jack Smith Correspondence [5 of 6]), July 7, 1997 (Map-case 1, Drawer F)